B. F. Wade Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
B. F. Wade Papers 1832-1886 (bulk 1852-1869)
MSS44263
Wade, B. F (Benjamin Franklin), 1800-1878
3,500 items 18 containers 4 linear feet 11 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, United States senator from Ohio, and Republican Party leader. Chiefly political correspondence relating to Wade’s career in the Senate as well as personal letters concerning his law practice and business. Includes printed speeches, maps, family letters, business records, and other material.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Briggs, James A., -1889--Correspondence.; Chase, Salmon P. (Salmon Portland), 1808-1873--Correspondence.; Cox, Jacob D. (Jacob Dolson), 1828-1900--Correspondence.; Davis, Henry Winter, 1817-1865--Correspondence.; De Gurowski, Adam G., count, 1805-1866--Correspondence.; Dennison, William, 1815-1882--Correspondence.; Forney, John W. (John Wien), 1817-1881--Correspondence.; Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881--Correspondence.; Geiger, Joseph H.--Correspondence.; Goodlow, William A.; Johnson, Andrew, 1808-1875--Impeachment.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865--Correspondence.; Paine, R. F. (Robert F.)--Correspondence.; Piatt, Donn, 1819-1891--Correspondence.; Rosecrans, William S. (William Starke), 1819-1898--Correspondence.; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872--Correspondence.; Smith, Green Clay, 1826-1895--Correspondence.; Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1814-1869--Correspondence.; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874--Correspondence.; Wade family.; Wade, B. F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1800-1878.
Organizations
Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United States. Congress. Joint Committee on the Conduct of the War.
Subjects
African Americans--Suffrage.; Elections--United States--1860.; Elections--United States--1864.; Elections--United States--1868.; Impeachments.; Practice of law--Ohio.; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877); Secession--Southern States.; Slaves--Emancipation--United States.
Places
Ohio--Commerce.; Ohio--Politics and government.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1849-1877.
Occupations
Lawyers.; Politicians.; Senators, U.S. Congress--Ohio.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of B. F. Wade, lawyer, United States senator from Ohio, and Republican Party leader, were given to the Library of Congress by Clara Wade Crosby, John Parsons Wade, and B. F. Wade in 1937.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of B. F. Wade are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on eleven reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1800. Oct. 27 Born, Feeding Hills, Mass.
1821 Moved to Andover, Ohio
1827 Admitted to Ohio bar
1827-1837 Practicing lawyer, Jefferson, Ohio
1835-1837 Prosecuting attorney, Ashtabula County, Ohio
1837 Elected to Ohio state senate
1841 Married Caroline M. Rosekrans
1847 Appointed judge, Third Judicial Circuit
1851-1869 United States senator
1852 Supported repeal of Fugitive Slave Law
1859 Supported homestead legislation
1860 Voted against Crittenden Compromise
1861-1865 Chairman, Joint Committee on the Conduct of the War
1864 Introduced Wade-Davis bill vetoed by Abraham Lincoln Issued Wade-Davis Manifesto criticizing Lincoln
1865 Introduced bill for enfranchisement of Negroes in the District of Columbia
1867 Elected president pro tempore of Senate
1868 Failed of re-election to Senate
1869 Resumed law practice; general counsel Northern Pacific Railroad Member, Board of Directors, Union Pacific Railroad
1871 Member, Santo Domingo Commission
1878, Mar. 2 Died, Jefferson, Ohio
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Benjamin Franklin Wade (1800-1878) span the years 1832-1886, but the bulk falls within the period of his services as United States senator, 1852-1869. The collection is arranged in two series: General Correspondence and Miscellany series.
A few letters concern Wade’s law practice and business affairs, but most are political in nature. Many are requests for help in obtaining civil or military appointments. Subjects include Ohio and national politics, including the elections of 1860, 1864, and 1868, secession, the Civil War, the Joint Committee on the Conduct of the War, emancipation, Reconstruction, Negro suffrage, and the impeachment of Andrew Johnson.
Among the correspondents are James A. Briggs, Salmon P. Chase, Jacob D. Cox, Henry Winter Davis, Count Adam G. De Gurowski, William Dennison, John W. Forney, James A. Garfield, Joseph H. Geiger, William A. Goodlow, Abraham Lincoln, R. F. Paine, Donn Paitt, William S. Rosescrans, William Henry Seward, Green Clay Smith, Edwin McMasters Stanton, and Charles Sumner.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in two series:
General Correspondence, 1832-1886
Miscellany, 1832-1881
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78044263
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 14,109.
- General Correspondence, 1832-1886 (Box 1-17, Reel 1-9)
  Correspondence, letters received, and Wade’s letters to his wife, Caroline M. Rosekrans.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1832, May 12-1852, Mar. 15 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1852, Mar. 19-1857, Nov. 23 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 1857, Dec. 8-1860, Nov. 7 (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - 1860, Nov. 9-1861, Feb. 24 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - 1861, Feb. 24-1862, Jan. 4 (Box 5, Reel 3)
  - 1862, Jan. 5-Mar. 5 (Box 6, Reel 3)
  - 1862, Mar. 6-May 31 (Box 7, Reel 4)
  - 1862, June 3-Dec. 29 (Box 8, Reel 4)
  - 1862, Dec. 31-1864, Jan. 17 (Box 9, Reel 5)
  - 1864, Jan. 18-1865, Feb. 21 (Box 10, Reel 5)
  - 1865, Feb. 24-1866, Apr. 4 (Box 11, Reel 6)
  - 1866, Apr. 16-1867, Feb. 18 (Box 12, Reel 6)
  - 1867, Feb. 19-July 9 (Box 13, Reel 7)
  - 1867, July 10-1868, Mar. 14 (Box 14, Reel 7)
  - 1868, Mar. 15-1869, Jan. 19 (Box 15, Reel 8)
  - 1869, Jan. 20-1873, Sept. 4 (Box 16, Reel 8)
  - 1874, Mar. 13-1886 Jan. 18, and undated (Box 17, Reel 9)
- Miscellany, 1832-1881 (Box 18, Reel 10-11)
  Miscellaneous material includes routine requests for government documents; printed speeches; letters of his son, James F. Wade, to his parents; maps; business records; and printed matter.
  Arranged by document type.
  - Letters of James F. Wade (son) to his parents, 1856-1881 (Box 18, Reel 10-11)
  - Requests for government documents, 1859-1869, (5 folders) (Box 18, Reel 10-11)
  - Speeches by Wade, 1856-1862 (Box 18, Reel 10-11)
  - Maps, circa 1860-circa 1870 (Box 18, Reel 10-11)
  - Business records, 1833-1853 (Box 18, Reel 10-11)
  - Printed matter, 1856-1870, (2 folders) (Box 18, Reel 10-11)